Keith Porcaro

919 389 3684 | keith@porca.ro

Academic Affiliations

Berkman Klein Center for Internet & Society at Harvard University

Fellow, 2017-18 Affiliate, 2018-present

Georgetown University Law Center

Adjunct Professor, 2017-present

 Co-designed and -taught a 4-credit practicum on Criminal Justice Technology, Policy, and Law. Students worked with partners on projects that explored how data and technology reframe criminal justice policy and practice. Our partners included the Maryland Governor's Office of Crime Control and Prevention, the Texas Indigent Defense Commission, Philadelphia District Attorney's Office, and the DC Office of the Attorney General.

Duke Center on Law and Technology

Research Affiliate, 2018-present

Professional Experience

Digital Public

Co-founder, 2017-present

- Digital Public builds governance models for data and technology projects.
- Sourced and executed client projects. Clients include:
 - Cincinnati Children's Hospital and Medical Center Developing data and network governance for "health learning networks": data-sharing collaborations of care centers, researchers, and patients.
 - Innovation, Science, and Economic Development (ISED) Canada For the innovation branch of the Canadian government, authored paper on the use of trusts as a data management tool.
 - City of Guelph-County of Wellington Contributed governance approaches to CAD\$10M-winning grant proposal for Canada's Smart Cities Challenge.
 - UNI Global Union Developed interactive primer to teach basic data governance principles to UNI's member unions.
 - Cape Cod Commercial Fishermen's Association Authored report, Building a fishermenfirst data ecosystem, that developed legal and technical models for small boat New England fisherman to set up a parallel data collection and analysis system.

SIMLab / FrontlineSMS

CTO / General Counsel, SIMLab, 2016-2017 Head of Technology and Development / General Counsel, SIMLab, 2015-2016 Legal Project Director, FrontlineSMS, 2014

Executed a \$1.5M Google.org-funded project to expedite land titling in Odisha, India. I spent
almost three months in Odisha, and worked with government officials and local non-profit
partners to scope, design, implement, and provide training on a text-message based system for
tracking the distribution of land titles to rural villagers in Odisha.

- Built US technology and access to justice portfolio. Clients included Duke Law School, Bay Area Legal Aid, Legal Aid of Nebraska, KIPP Delta, Mississippi Access to Justice Commission, Nonprofit Risk Management Center, and DC Public Library.
- Designed data protection policies and procedures for European Commission-funded research project on community policing in post-conflict countries.
- Conducted technology trainings for civil society organizations in Iraq, Myanmar, and India.
- Responsible for SIMLab's technical and legal infrastructure, including grantee compliance, contracting, and managing entities in US and Kenya.

Uncharted Play, COO, 2012

Reboot, Content Strategist / Manager, Legal & Operations, 2011-12 Web Developer (Co-op), Global Web Design Team, Lenovo, 2006-07

Independent projects

- Detain/Release and other teaching simulations (2017-present) I designed and built Detain/Release, a web-based simulation to teach students, lawyers, and policymakers about the framing power of algorithmic risk assessments at pretrial. With Jason Tashea, I developed a lesson plan for teaching Detain/Release, along with other tools that use the simulation's underlying technical framework. In 2017, I developed a paper-based tabletop exercise that invited students to conduct a mock evaluation of a prison re-entry program in Virginia.
- Peer-to-Peer Housing Referral System (2018-19). For a consortium of legal aid organizations, I
 designed, managed, and built a legal referral system for housing cases in Alameda County,
 California.
- LIFT Dane (2018). For Legal Action of Wisconsin, I contributed technology design and grantwriting to a \$1M-winning proposal for Schmidt Futures' Alliance for the American Dream competition.

Talks, Publications, Media

Selected Talks

- "Data governance for learning networks" (keynote), Learning Networks Conference, 2019
- "Rethinking Health Data Governance", Yale Law & Technology Speaker Series, Yale Law School, 2019
- "Dirty Data, Bad Decisions", CogX, 2019
- Guest Lecture, "Detain/Release," Suffolk University School of Law, Fall 2019.
- Guest Lecture, "The Current and Future State of Legal Self-Help Technology," Laboratory Seminar in Applied Design and Legal Empowerment, Northeastern University School of Law, Summer 2018.
- How technology fails us, and what we can do about it. SAGE Ocean, SAGE Publishing, June 2018.
- "Too crazy to fail? A bold vision for the future of data governance", CogX, June 2018.
- Roll for initiative. Suffolk Law School, 2018 Clinical Innovation Conference.
- Conversations on Public Impact: How data trusts can preserve and protect your digital initiatives (webinar). Digital.gov, March 2018.
- Design Workshop, Duke Law Eviction Diversion Program / Civil Justice Clinic, Duke Law School, February 2018.
- In trust, data. Legal Services Corporation, 2018 Innovations in Technology Conference

- Workshop, "Access Tech Tools Initiative", Duke Law Clinical Programs / Center on Law and Technology, Duke Law School, February 2017.
- How I learned to stop worrying and love evaluations. Legal Services Corporation, 2017 Technology Innovation Grants Conference.
- Making Legal Services Explorable. Legal Services Corporation, 2017 Technology Innovation Grants Conference.
- Thinking in Ecosystems. Legal Services Corporation. 2016 Technology Innovation Grants Conference.
- Making Complexity Friendly. Legal Services Corporation. 2016 Technology Innovation Grants Conference.
- Trusts for Digital Governance (with Sean McDonald). RightsCon, 2016.

Selected Publications

- "Navigating the dark forest: health data governance in the age of machine learning" forthcoming.
- "Detain/Release: Simulating algorithmic risk assessments at pretrial", Berkman Klein Center, 2019.
- "Digital Land Lab", World Bank Land & Poverty Conference, 2015.
- Whispering When Everyone is Listening: Technology Deployments in High-Risk Environments (with Laura Walker Hudson). Communications technology and humanitarian delivery: challenges and opportunities for security risk management, European Interagency Security Forum, 2014
- "Private Ordering and Orphan Works: Our Least Worst Hope?", Duke Law & Technology Review, 2011.

Media

- Fastcase 50 Honoree 2019
- "10 Questions: Crafting tech solutions for legal aid" (interview), ABA Journal. June 2016

Education

JD, Duke University, 2011

Pro Bono Certificate

BSFS, Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, 2008

Major: International Politics

Concentration: International Development

Bar Admission

California, 2011 (#281464)